Guide to the Iselin Family Papers and Photographs 1880–1991 MS 3076
New-York Historical Society
Iselin family papers and photographs
1880–1991
New-York Historical Society
Iselin (Family)
MS 3076
1.668 Linear feet (in 4 document boxes and 1 oversize folder).
A small collection of papers and photographs documenting the Iselin family of New York, particularly the immediate descendants of banker Columbus O'Donnell Iselin (1851–1933) and his wife, Edith Colford (Jones) Iselin (1854–1930), as well as their Jones and O'Donnell forbears.
Conditions Governing Access
Open to qualified researchers. Except for one oversize folder, all of this collection is stored offsite and advance notice is required for use. Please contact manuscripts@nyhistory.org prior to your research visit to coordinate access. Keep in mind that it will take between two (2) and five (5) business days for collections to arrive, and you should plan your research accordingly.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Frederick William Byron Jr. in two parts: 2018 (accession no. MS-2018-047) and 2019 (accession no. MS-2019-032).
Arrangement
The Iselin Family Papers and Photographs are organized in three series:
Series I.
Iselin family, 1892–1991
Series II.
Related families, 1913, 1918, undated
Series III.
Photographs, 1880–1948
Biographical note
Columbus O'Donnell Iselin (1851–1933), son of Adrian Georg and Eleanora (O'Donnell) Iselin, married Edith Colford Jones (1854–1930), daughter of Lewis Colford and Catherine Margaretta (Berryman) Jones (circa 1829–1910). Among the children of Columbus and Edith Iselin were two sons, Lewis Iselin (1879–1928) and O'Donnell Iselin (1884–1971). Lewis married Marie Emilie de Neufville (1883–1979), and together they had three children: Columbus O'Donnell Iselin II (1904–1971), Marie (Iselin) LaFarge (1907–1979), and Lewis Iselin Jr. (1913–1990), who married Sarah Cary Curtis (1915–1998).
[All underlined names are represented by documents and/or photographs in the collection.]
Scope and Contents
While the bulk of the collection focuses on banker Lewis Iselin (1879–1928) and his wife, Marie Emilie (de Neufville) Iselin (1883–1979), scattered and seemingly disparate materials—bank statements, correspondence, school essays and report cards, wills and estate inventories, genealogical tables and memoirs—provide a picture of the wider Iselin family, as well as their O'Donnell and Jones connections.
New York (State) -- Genealogy.; Inventories of decedents' estates -- New York (State) -- New York.; Bank statements.; Essays.; Estate inventories.; Genealogical tables.; Household inventories.; Letters (correspondence); Memoirs.; Photographs.; Photograph albums.; Report cards.; Wills.; Iselin (Family); Jones (Family); O'Donnell (Family); Union Club of the City of New York.; Iselin, Columbus O'Donnell, 1851–1933.; Iselin, Columbus O'Donnell, II, 1904–1971.; Iselin, Edith Colford (Jones), 1854–1930.; Iselin, Lewis, 1879-1928.; Iselin, Lewis, Jr., 1913–1990.; Iselin, Marie de Neufville, 1883-1979.; Jones, Catherine Margaretta (Berryman), approximately 1829–1910.
- Series I. Iselin family, 1892–1991
  - Columbus O'Donnell Iselin (1851–1933). Indenture, 1919 May 29 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 1)
    Scope and Contents
    Transfer of corporate stock of the City of New York for the construction of the Rapid Transit Railroad to his grandson, Lewis Iselin Jr. (1913–1990).
  - Edith Colford (Jones) Iselin (1854–1930). Copy of a letter to her children and grandchildren, 1922, 1930 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 2)
    Photostat / facsimile of a letter dated February 2, 1922 from Edith C. Iselin to her children and grandchildren. With an embossed black leather (?) pouch and a cover letter from Columbus O'Donnell Iselin passing Edith's letter to his grandson, Lewis Iselin [Jr.], May 5, 1930.
  - Lewis Iselin (1879–1928). "School Days of Lewis & O'Donnell", 1892–1907 (Offsite-box 1, Volume 1)
    Embossed red leather (?) scrapbook containing various school publications, e.g., the Cutler School Honor Roll (1892–1902), Cutler School catalogs (1899, 1902), The Cutler Fortnightly (1903), The Standard (a publication of the Knickerbocker Greys?) (1898–1899), leaflets and ephemera from Columbia University and Harvard College, as well as receipts, bills, correspondence, and school essays by the Iselin brothers, Lewis (1879–1928) and O'Donnell (1884–1971).
  - Lewis Iselin (1879–1928). Schoolwork [essays], 1895–1902 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 3)
  - Lewis Iselin (1879–1928). "Letters of Lewis Iselin", 1895–1903 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 1)
    In a red leather (?), embossed portfolio.
  - Lewis Iselin (1879–1928). Receipt, Black, Starr & Frost, Jewellers [sic] and Silversmiths, 438 Fifth Avenue, 1903 October 8 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 2)
  - Lewis Iselin (1879–1928). Decennial Record of the Class of 1903, Columbia University in the City of New York, 1914 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 3)
    Lewis Iselin on p. 85.
  - Lewis Iselin (1879–1928). "Appraisal and Inventory of Household Furnishings Belonging to Lewis Iselin, Contained In and On the Premises Situated at 16 West 52nd Street, New York City," by the Equitable Appraisal Company, 1920 February 17 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 4)
    Covers each room in the five-floor home. 105 pages.
  - Lewis Iselin (1879–1928). Union Club resolution marking the death of Lewis Iselin, 1928 April 11 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 5)
    Engrossed copy of a resolution passed to mark the death of Lewis Iselin, who served as the Union Club's governor, 1915–1927, and treasurer, 1917–1927.
  - Marie (de Neufville) Iselin (1883–1979). List of passengers, R.M.S. "Queen Mary", 1952 September 4 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 6)
    Includes "Mrs. Lewis Iselin."
  - Marie (de Neufville) Iselin (1883–1979). Last will and testament [2 copies], 1958 July 25 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 7)
  - Marie (de Neufville) Iselin (1883–1979). Estate papers, 1979 November 1–6 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 8)
  - Marie (de Neufville) Iselin (1883–1979). Estate appraisal, 1979 December 12 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 9)
    "Appraisal of the Estate of Marie DeN. Iselin, Deceased," by Masterson & O'Connell & Albano Co., covering each room of the apartment at 860 Park Avenue, as well as Mrs. Iselin's jewelry. 63 pages.
  - Columbus O'Donnell Iselin II (1904–1971). Financial statements, The Farmer's Loan and Trust Company, 1922–1923 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 10)
  - Lewis Iselin Jr. (1913–1990). Wills, powers of attorney, 1975, 1976, 1987 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 1)
    Wills and powers of attorney for Lewis Iselin Jr. and his wife, Sarah Cary (Curtis) Iselin (1915–1998).
  - Lewis Iselin Jr. (1913–1990). Estate appraisal, 1991 April 14 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 2)
    Jan G. Andersen & Assoc. "Qualified appraisal prepared at the request of the Estate of Lewis Iselin."
  - Lewis Iselin Jr. (1913–1990). Maine tax papers, 1991 November 5 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 3)
  - Iselin family. "Stammtafel der / Genealogical Tree ISELIN von Basel", 1948 (Oversize large, Item 1)
    Nach dem Familienbuch von Fr. Weiss un Beiträgen von Hr. Dr. Felix Iselin-Merian, ergänzt und gezeichnet von Hans Lengweiler, Basel-Luzern, Im Febr./März 1948. No. 14. Measures 28.5 x 41 inches.
  - Iselin family. Gustav Adolf Wanner. Seit 600 Jahren in Basel: Lebensbilder aus der Familie Iselin, 1964 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 4)
    With tipped-in letter from O'Donnell Iselin (1884–1971), May 1965.
- Series II. Related families, 1913, 1918, undated
  - Jones family. Marie Caroline de Trobriand Post. The Descendants of John Jones and John Mason, 1913 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 5)
  - Jones family. Helen A. Wissmann, "Memories of the Past", undated (Offsite-box 3, Folder 6)
    Photocopy of 23-page typescript plus 10-page appendix. Helen (Jones) Wissmann was the sister of Edith Colford (Jones) Iselin (1854–1930).
  - O'Donnell family. "Antique Milesianæ Familiæ De O'Donnell", undated (Oversize large, Item 2)
    Facsimile genealogy and family tree of the O'Donnell family (apparently originally "Niall"), in Latin, on a scroll of 4 attached sheets with an overall measurement of 18 x 87 inches.
  - O'Donnell family. Allan Macsherry. "The O'Donnell Family", 1918 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 7)
    15-page typescript.
- Series III. Photographs, 1880–1948
  - Album. "Marie Iselin", 1881–1929 (Offsite-box 4, Enclosure 1)
    Includes photographs of Columbus O'Donnell Iselin (1851–1933), Lewis Iselin (1879–1928), O'Donnell Iselin (1884–1971), Marie (de Neufville) Iselin (1883–1979), Columbus O'Donnell Iselin II (1904–1971), Marie (Iselin) La Farge (1907–1979), and Lewis Iselin Jr. (1913–1990).
  - Album. "Mrs. Lewis Colford Jones", 1900 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 8)
    An album of five studio portraits, plus two loose prints of Catherine Margaretta (Berryman) Jones (circa 1829–1910), Mrs. Lewis Colford Jones, mother of Edith Colford (Jones) Iselin (1854–1930).
  - Loose photographs [3 folders], 1880–1948 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 9–11)
    Includes photographs of various members of the extended Iselin family, such as Columbus O'Donnell Iselin (1851–1933), Edith Colford (Jones) Iselin (1854–1930), Lewis Iselin (1879–1928), O'Donnell Iselin (1884–1971), Marie (de Neufville) Iselin (1883–1979), Columbus O'Donnell Iselin II (1904–1971), Eleanor "Nora" Emmet (Lapsley) Iselin (1907–1971), Marie (Iselin) La Farge (1907–1979), Lewis Iselin Jr. (1913–1990), Francis "Frank" and Helen (Jones) Wissmann.